Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 13, Publications/Clippings, 1926-1992
  - Subseries 1, Hurwitz, 1926-1992
    - no title (Box C009)
      - London ’82 -- National Film Theatre retrospective, 1982 (Folder 8)
      - Cincinnati -- "Hard Times" -- Film Society screenings:D.W.A.W.D. etc. 5/82, 1982 (Folder 9)
        Flyers and mailings for "Hard Times: Social Documentaries of the 1930s," a series sponsored by the Cincinnati Film Society featuring Hurwitz. The folder also contains newsletters, press releases, and clippings.
    - no title (Box C011)
      - [European trip], 1966 (Folder 2)
        Materials from the 1966 European trip, including correspondence, Cinémathèque Française schedule, a publication from the 9th International Festival of Short and Documentary Films in Leipzig, notes, and tourist items.
      - [Envelope labeled: Notes -- 1966 Europe trip] (Folder 4)
        Notes made by Hurwitz, including a draft of a Cinémathèque Française talk.
      - [Letters to Peggy Lawson], 1958-1966; undated (Folder Folder 1)
    - no title (Box C016)
      - L.H. material for screening info, ca. 1975 (Folder 15)
        Copies of flyers and newspaper clippings about Hurwitz to be used as promotional material for screenings.
      - Film school -- curr. -- New School, etc., 1962; 1966-1967 (Folder 29)
    - no title (Box C018)
      - [Box labeled: Scrapbook material], 1942-1953; 1961; undated (Folder 5)
        Newspaper articles, press releases, publications from throughout Hurwitz's career to be used in a scrapbook. Materials were originally housed in a black drop-front box.
      - [Newspapers--The Jerusalem Post and Les Lettres Françaises], 1961 (Folder 5a)
      - [Folder labeled:Alice in Wonderland clippings etc.], 1948-1953 (Folder 5e)
      - [Time magazine -- article on Alice in Wonderland], 1951 (Folder 5g)
    - no title (Box C004)
      - [Correspondence and newspaper clippings -- Oulu, Finland], 1980 (Folder 3)
      - [Copy of Filmihullu], 1975 (Folder 11)
        Issue of Finnish film magazine Filmihullu[1975]. In Finnish.
      - [Envelope labeled: Letter regarding H.A. Potamkin and Salt of the Earth material], 1977; 1981 (Folder 15)
    - no title (Box C022)
      - Finland, 1979-1981 (Folder 6)
        Three issues of the Finnish magazine Filmihullu and an issue of the Finnish newspaper Helsingin Sanomat with article about Hurwitz. In Finnish.
      - Ghent Festival: 1981 (Folder 15a)
      - Leipzig Festival '81, 1981 (Folder 16a)
        Issue of Filmspiegel magazine with an article about the Leipzig festival, and publications from the State Film Archive of the GDR regarding the program "American Social Documentary Retrospective -- USA Documentaries 1930-1945," which featured several of Hurwitz's films. In German.
      - Festival dei Popoli: Florence -- 1981, 1981-1982 (Folder 16b)
        Materials related to the 1981 Festival dei Popoli, Florence, Italy, including correspondence, newspaper clippings, a festival catalog, and bulletins. In English and Italian.
      - Filme-- Verena Zimmermann translation, 1981 (Folder 2a)
        Profile of Hurwitz for the Sept./Oct. 1981 issue of the German publication Filme: Neues and Altes vom Kino(includes photocopies of both the profile and the entire issue), with English translations and corrections. In English and German.
      - [Copy of Filme profile on Hurwitz], ca. 1981 (Folder 2b)
        Early photocopy of the profile of Hurwitz to be featured in the Sept./Oct. 1981 issue of the German publication Filme: Neues and Altes vom Kino. In German.
      - Berlin Film Festival -- Feb. 1981 -- Material related to Dialogue with a Woman Departed and Leo Hurwitz (programs, notes, articles, prizes, etc.) (Folder 3b)
      - Berlin Film Festival 2/81 -- Extra material related to Dialogue with a Woman Departed and Leo Hurwitz, 1981 (Folder 3c)
      - [Festival Internacional de Cinema da Figueira da Foz -- catalog], 1981 (Folder 7b)
        1981 festival catalog. In Portuguese.
      - [Festival Internacional de Cinema da Figueira da Foz -- festival material], 1981 (Folder 7c)
        Folder containing festival material, including a festival pass, correspondence, maps, color screenshots, and various publications and tourist guides. In Portuguese and English.
      - [Festival Internacional de Cinema da Figueira da Foz -- programs of festival/pages on films], 1981 (Folder 7d)
        Schedules, daily programs, copies of Hurwitz information from catalog, and notes. In Portuguese and English.
      - Verleih Genossenschaft promotional material, 1981 (Folder 9a)
      - Openings: German cities -- promotional material, 1981-1982 (Folder 9b)
      - Clippings/reviews -- Germany, 1981 (Folder 9c)
      - [Copy of Bär Fax Magazine with Hurwitz Interview], 1981 (Folder 9d)
        Issue of Bär Fax Magazine, "Berlin's English language magazine," with an interview with Hurwitz about Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Film Verleih Genossenschaft: Swiss showings press material, 1981-1982 (Folder 9f)
    - no title (Box C026)
      - [Brandon International Film Rental catalog], 1966 (Folder 3c)
        1966 film rental catalog for English language feature films.Strange Victory is listed.
    - no title (Box C030)
      - Press clippings --Lippold, 1966 (Folder 60)
    - no title (Box C034)
      - [U.S.A.-- awards, festivals], 1956-1957 (Folder 5a)
        Communication regarding the awarding of the George Washington Honor medal to U.S.A.; brochure for the 1957 Festival for the Arts at the First Unitarian Church; clipping from Rushes newspaper regarding the 10th International Edinburgh Film Festival; issue of Pan American World Airways' System Sales Clipper in-house newsletter with an article regarding U.S.A..
    - no title (Box C038)
      - [[Envelope labeled:Cineaste magazine interview], 1974 (Folder 10)
        Correspondence regarding Cineaste magazine interview with Hurwitz; typed and handwritten transcriptions of questions and answers with notes, corrections; final version of interview.
      - [Envelope labeled: N.Y.U. -- Struggle vs. dean 1973, plus misc.] (Folder 13)
    - no title (Box C040)
      - Film school idea -- final draft -- correspondence -- Lincoln Center, Buffalo, Rockefeller, 1965-1969 (Folder 8)
    - no title (Box C041)
      - L.H. film descriptions, also L.H. film lists, 1976; 1981; undated (Folder 30)
        Contains synopses and filmographic information about Hurwitz's films taken from retrospective program notes, calendars, and catalogs. Venues include the Pacific Film Archive, the Hague Filmhuis, San Francisco State University Cinémathèque, Festival Internacional de Cinema, and Figueira da Foz.
      - L.H. film "mentions" (misc. leaflets, programs, schedules, clippings etc.), 1976; 1983-1986 (Folder 51)
        Pamphlets, clippings, calendars, flyers, and other publications mentioning Hurwitz and/or his films.
    - no title (Box C043)
      - Folder 3i:H.A.T.W.E. copies Les Lettres' review, Paris, 9/21/61, undated (Folder 3i)
      - [Envelope labeled: Clippings -- Milan 4/80], 1980 (Folder 6d)
        Clippings and photocopies of Italian newspaper articles covering the program "La classe operaia nel cinema Americano (1930-1980)"/"The Working Class in American Cinema (1930-1980)" held in Milan, April 1980. In Italian.
      - [Loose correspondence], 1980 (Folder 6e)
    - no title (Box C049)
      - Les Lettres Françaises 9/27/61 review, 1961 (Folder 1)
        Seven photocopies of an article about Hurwitz titled "Un poète cosmique de l'image: Léo Hurwitz" (in French).
    - no title (Box C050)
      - Iowa correspondence, etc, 1974-1975 (Folder 3)
    - no title (Box C055)
      - [Hurwitz, Leo -- correspondence, clippings, 1940s], 1945-1946 (Folder 14)
        Clippings and correspondence regarding "Freedom Road." Includes clippings from the Los Angeles Daily News,The Los Angeles Times, and Hotel & Club Voice regarding the upcoming film adaptation of Freedom Road; and letters from Film Music Associates, artist Gyula Zilzer (with exhibition brochures), Mordecai Gorelik, and Salem Ludwig, inquiring about work on the production. Also includes 10/5/1946 New Dynamo supplement; the 1945 Annual Meteorological Summary; and an envelope from the U.S. Department of Commerce Weather Bureau containing Monthly Meteorological Summaries from 1942-1946.
    - no title (Box C058)
      - [Clippings and publications], 1966-1970; 1977; 1980 (Folder 4)
        Clippings and publications found loose in Box C058, including a 1977 Bulgarian magazine with an article on the FIAF XXXIII Congress in Varna, Bulgaria, and an interview with Hurwitz (in Bulgarian); a 2/14/1977 issue of International Bulletin; clippings from The New York Review and The New York Times; a 1970 Brandon Films, Inc., catalog; a 12/1966 issue of Ramparts magazine; and a 1980 issue of The Independent, featuring an interview with Manny Kirchheimer. Also includes three invitations to the 1976 commencement ceremony at Kirkland College, homeowner's insurance document, and Hurwitz's recommendation for a student's NEH Youthgrant.
      - In Search of Hart Crane, 1964; 1971 (Folder 5)
        Clippings and correspondence related to Hurwitz's film, including two photocopies of The New York Times review; a letter from a professor at Reed College; and a carbon of a letter from "Laurie Liberty" [Hurwitz?] to the William Morris Agency inquiring after a Hart Crane biopic referenced by actress Carrie Snodgress in an attached 1971 Christian Science Monitor interview. Also includes a photocopy of a 11/27/1964 Time magazine article mentioning Essay on Death.
      - In Search of Hart Crane publicity materials & reviews & letters re: film, 1967; 1969 (Folder 12)
      - The Sun and Richard Lippold reviews, 1966 (Folder 14)
      - Here at the H2O's Edge, Capdenac piece & translations, also reviews: Lippold, Hart Crane, 1966; undated (Folder 15)
        Undated Les Lettres Françaises clipping (original and multiple photocopies) featuring Michel Capdenac's article about Here at the Waters' Edge(in French, with separate typed English translation). Includes photocopies of the 1966 The New York Times review of In Search of Hart Crane and The New York Herald Tribune review of The Sun and Richard Lippold.
    - no title (Box C061)
      - Europe reviews, 1981 (Folder 1)
      - Washington -- AFI Masters -- including International Herald Tribune, 1983 (Folder 5)
        Clippings from the International Herald Tribune,The Washington Post, and The Washington Times about Hurwitz.The Times piece takes the form of a Q&A.
      - Swedish reviews 1982 -- Stockholm masters (Folder 8)
      - [Boston articles], 1992 (Folder 9)
        Copies of articles from The Boston Phoenix on the Institute of Contemporary Art's series "Montage and Modern Life: 1919-1942." Film and Photo League films made up part of the screening program.
      - Master translations: Épernay articles, 1983 (Folder 13)
      - Master: cover/reviews from Europe, 1981-1982 (Folder 14)
      - Master reviews from Europe with cover, 1981 (Folder 15)
      - Master: Zimmermann pieces, 1982 (Folder 16)
      - Original "Responses" (less full), 1981 (Folder 18)
      - Mabrouki -- Algiers original translation, 1985 (Folder 19)
      - Maine: McKibben review, poster,Portland Express story, leaflet for Film Market, 1982 (Folder 21)
    - no title (Box C062)
      - Vermont Peace Festival, 1987 (Folder 21)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's appearance at the 2nd Vermont World Peace Film Festival, University of Vermont 6/28-7/2/1987, including programs; nametag; business cards and notes; hotel and travel receipts; and a syllabus from a class with Michael Selig. Also includes issues of The Gadfly and Vanguard Press with articles on the festival, and a related clipping from the Burlington Free Press.
    - no title (Box C068)
      - Publicity clippings --Verdict for Tomorrow-- Eichmann -- for trial scrapbook, 1961-1962 (Folder 7)
        Clippings on Verdict for Tomorrow; announcement and program for the Peabody Awards.
    - no title (Box C069)
      - [Strange Victory articles], 1950; 1958; 1972 (Folder 1)
    - no title (Box C070)
      - [Strange Victory 1964 reissue, reviews] (Folder 19)
      - [Strange Victory and Native Land screenings, Columbia University, 1972] (Folder 22)
      - [Strange Victory reviews (copies)], undated (Folder 24)
    - no title (Box C073)
      - American Theatre Wing, 1950; 1956 (Folder 10)
        Includes a 2/3/1949 New York Times clipping about the expansion of the Dramatic Workshop Film Department of the New School of Social Research to include television production. Hurwitz is mentioned as returning from a leave-of-absence.
    - no title (Box C089)
      - Zurich/Basel, 1983 (Folder 37)
        Materials related to a 1983 Leo Hurwitz film retrospectives at the Stadtkino Basel, Basel, and Filmpodium Kino, Zurich, Switzerland. Includes booklets, calendars, and related magazine and newspaper articles.
      - Berlin(e) Academy screening of D.W.A.W.D., poster, 1983 (Folder 38)
      - Finnish articles, 1977; 1979; 1984 (Folder 39)
        Three issues of the Finnish film magazine Filmihullu; the January 1979 issue featuring an article on Hurwitz. Also includes a January 1984 Esquire magazine article on Larry Gross's collection of photographs featuring African Americans.
      - Swedish, Scandin. seminars, 1983; 1986 (Folder 40)
      - Rome 1988, 1988-1989 (Folder 41)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's 1988 trip to Rome and his participation in the conference "From the Lumières to Our Times: Heading towards Cinema's Centenary" at the Università degli studi di Roma "La Spaienza" [now the Spapienza University of Rome], including Italian newspaper clippings about Hurwitz and conference notes. In Italian and English.
      - Helsinki seminars etc. 3/31-4/9/89, 1988-1989 (Folder 49)
    - no title (Box C090)
      - [Bag labeled: Clippings, etc. -- Sinking Creek (Nashville)], 1978 (Folder 4)
        Material related to Hurwitz's visit to Vanderbilt University as part of the 1978 Sinking Creek Film Celebration. Includes conference materials, newspaper clippings, and promotional items. In English and French.
      - Envelope labeled: Publicity material, mostly in 60s -- miscellaneous], 1959-1967 (Folder 6a)
        Includes press releases for The New York Times and Here at the Waters' Edge and a brochure for Haiku. Also includes clippings regarding "The Scarlet Letter," the Strange Victory rerelease, and Hurwitz and the Eichmann Trial. In English and French.
      - [Envelope labeled: Misc. publicity material], 1967-1976 (Folder 6b)
    - no title (Box C092)
      - Materials to be translated, 1981-1985 (Folder 11)
      - [Folder labeled: Europe trip notes, letters, addresses, schedules, etc. 1981] (Folder 13)
    - no title (Box C094)
      - [Personal correspondence, speaking engagement notices,Dialogue with a Woman Departed promotional material], 1970; 1982 (Folder 23)
    - no title (Box C096)
      - L.H. miscellaneous, 1963 (Folder 18b)
    - no title (Box C098)
      - [Publications referencing Hurwitz's death], 1991 (Folder 8)
    - no title (Box C099)
      - [Correspondence], 1976-1980; 1989 (Folder 2a)
        Includes an issue of Grand Valley State Colleges' newspaper The Paper devoted to Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C101)
      - [Envelope labeled: 1/4" cassettes -- LH talks and interviews], 1979; 1988-1989 (Folder 17)
    - no title (Box C102)
      - [Clippings, film festival correspondence, SDIG correspondence], 1960-1965 (Folder 12)
        Includes clippings, correspondence, and notes. Clippings include the Les Lettres Française article about Hurwitz, and articles regarding loyalty oaths, civil rights, the Cold War, and Israel.
    - no title (Box C103)
      - [Envelope labeled: Iowa stories, copies], 1975 (Folder 2b)
      - Résumés etc. LTH, 1972-1975 (Folder 2g)
      - [Envelope labeled: Misc. -- clippings & publicity material re: L.H.], 1975; 1978; 1979 (Folder 8)
      - [Envelope labeled: Florence Festival dei Popoli catalog 1976 inc. N.L.], 1979 (Folder 13)
        Catalog for the 1976 Festival de Popoli, XVII Rassegna Internazionale del Film di Documentazione Sociale in Florence Italy, featuring a screening of Native Land. In Italian. Also includes cover note from Gordon Hitchens (in English).
      - [Envelope labeled: Clippings, etc. L.H.], 1966-1967; 1975; undated (Folder 16)
        Includes photocopies of newspaper reviews of The Sun and Richard Lippold from The New York Times and the New York-Herald Tribune; letter from DEFA Studios regarding a television interview with Hurwitz; a Winter 1975/1975 screening calendar for the New American Filmmakers Series at the Whitney Museum of American Art featuring Native Land; and a partial undated transcript of Hurwitz discussing his films.
    - no title (Box C104)
      - [Envelope labeled: Brandon stuff], 1974 (Folder 13b)
      - Reviews, 1966-1967 (Folder 17d)
        Reviews of The Sun and Richard Lippold[1966] and In Search of Hart Crane[1966]. Also includes the Les Lettres Françaises article about Hurwitz, with English translation.
    - no title (Box C156)
      - Dialogue with a Woman Departed-- Europe reviews -- with Xeroxes and rough transla, 1981 (Folder 4)
        Foreign-language reviews of Dialogue with a Woman Departed, with English translations. In Portuguese, Dutch, Swedish, German, and English.
      - [Essay on Death clippings], 1964 (Folder 13)
    - no title (Box C158)
      - Clippings re: "Scarlet Letter", 1962 (Folder 15)
        Newspaper clippings regarding Hurwitz's planned adaptation of The Scarlet Letter.
    - no title (Box C160)
      - NET --Essay on Death, etc., 1964-1967 (Folder 6)
      - [Copies of articles,Here at the Waters' Edge advertisement text], 1980-1986 (Folder 18)
      - Leo: Obituary, condolences, 1991 (Folder 28)
        Includes a clipping Hurwitz's The New York Times obituary, and condolence letters to Nell Burlingham and Tom Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C172)
      - Personal biography -- "quotes" --Native Land and Strange Victory, ca. 1942; ca. 1949-1956 (Folder 16)
        Copies of Hurwitz's résumé, related notes, and a partial listing of film/TV projects. Also includes Hurwitz's essay "Notes on 25 Years"; quotes from reviews of Strange Victory,Native Land, and An Evening for Richard Rodgers; a Film News clipping regarding On This Day; suggested film programs, symposia, and Cine club conferences; and correspondence from Robert D. Field and Gilbert Seldes.
      - Masters -- Leo Hurwitz, 1982 (Folder 30)
      - [Bag labeled: Masters,Who's Who in the East], undated (Folder 31)
        Photocopies of Hurwitz's entry in Who's Who in the East.
      - [Cinema Journal], 1975 (Folder 34)
    - no title (Box C178)
      - Mandatory retirement, 1973-1974 (Folder 6)
    - no title (Box C186)
      - [File pocket labeled: College papers and notes, school poems], 1926-1931 (Folder 1)
        Materials dating from Hurwitz's time at Harvard College, including college essays and a photocopy of his dissertation; fine-arts syllabi and notes; class of 1930 personal profile;World Telegraph clippings of reviews written by Hurwitz; photocopies of Hurwitz's poems and published letters; notes on a proposed animated film; and clippings from The New Republic and The Dial.
      - [Folder labeled: Film and scrapbook stuff], 1936-1938; undated (Folder 4f)
    - no title (Box C190)
      - [Unlabeled envelope with German film magazine Zoom], 1990 (Folder 5)
      - Letters to Peggy from J.H. Lawson, 1962-1963; 1968; 1971; 1977; 1979; 1990 (Folder 6)
        Letters to Peggy Lawson from her father-in-law John Howard "Jack" Lawson and his wife Susan ("Mom"), most sent while they were visiting the U.S.S.R. Also includes several newspaper obituaries of Hurwitz, enclosed letters to Nelly Burlingham from Jane Dudley; and letters to Hurwitz from Larry S. Ceplair, Bill Nichols, Susan Lawson, Grand Valley State Colleges, and the British Film Institute's National Film Archive.
      - [Photography publications], 1948; 1949; 1969; 1974; 1989; 1991; undated (Folder 7)
        Photography magazines, booklets, and brochures, including a Spring 1949 issue of Photo Notes;Vision Is My Dwelling Place, a memoir of Sidney Meyers written by Jay Leyda; and two copies of This Is the Photo League. Also includes a Lionel Berman memorial booklet; a cover letter from the Leo Dratfield Endowment which originally accompanied Hurwitz's Leo Award certificate; a holiday card from J. Winiewicz, Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs; an April 1991 Museum of Modern Art calendar, featuring a memorial screening of Native Land; and a brochure for an Ursula Suess exhibition in Munich, with a letter and artwork from Suess.
      - [Harvard Magazine, Sinking Creek Film Scrapbook], 1981; 1991 (Folder 8)
      - [Sightlines journal], 1989 (Folder 12)
    - no title (Box C192)
      - [Envelope labeled: Programs and photostats of reviews of Native Land], ca. 1942 (Folder 3h)
    - no title (Box C218)
      - Address, etc. from cutting room wall, 1967-1968 (Folder 1c)
      - [Film journals], 1975-1980 (Folder 3)
        Fall 1975 issue of Cinema Journal featuring Hurwitz's essay "One Man's Voyage"; July/August 1978 issue of Cinema Nuovo featuring an article on Hurwitz [in Italian]; two copies of the 2/79 issue of Filmkritik devoted to Hurwitz [in German]; Vol. 13, Number 1 1980 issue of Film Library Quarterly featuring articles on the Film and Photo League; and 1977 issue of Filmihullu featuring an interview with Hurwitz [in Finnish].
    - no title (Box C221)
      - [Hurwitz obituaries], 1991 (Folder 5)
    - no title (Box C226)
      - [Hurwitz memorial gathering flyers], 1991 (Folder 8)
        Copies of flyers announcing a 3/30/1991 memorial gathering for Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C227)
      - Material for scrapbook, 1942-1951 (Folder 5)
        Promotional flyers, letters, union testimonials, newspaper clippings, and reviews for Native Land; newspaper clippings about Paul Strand, the signing to Vanguard Films, Hurwitz joining CBS, "Freedom Road,"Folksay, the dramatic workshop film department where Hurwitz did a seminar on film techniques, the United Nations films, and Strange Victory; brochure from Brandon Films promoting Native Land,People of the Cumberland, and other films; promotional program for a performance of the score of Native Land; catalog for The Writers School by the League of American Writers where Hurwitz taught a workshop in documentary film writing; invitation from the Hollywood Writers Mobilization for a presentation by Joris Ivens and screening of films including Native Land; program for the 1943 Writer's Congress; program for tribute to President Roosevelt exhibition, featuring Hurwitz on the committee of photography; reviews of CBS programs; review of They Were There(1944), interview of Woody Guthrie produced and directed by Hurwitz.
      - U.N. peace film, 1950 (Folder 6)
      - [Bag labeled: Xeroxes "Scrap Book" --Native Land and Strange Victory], ca. 1942 (Folder 7)
      - [Article on Hurwitz at University of Iowa; commencement address by Robin Felid], 1965; 1975 (Folder 25)
        Copy of newspaper article on Hurwitz as artist in residence at the University of Iowa; 1965 commencement address delivered by Robin Felid titled "Creative Sensibility."
      - Cinémathèque "homage", 1966-1967 (Folder 26)
        Documents related to the Cinémathèque Française's homage to Hurwitz, including draft introduction titled "Leo H. and the Documentary in the U.S.A.," newspaper clipping with list of screenings, and flyer/schedule.
      - NYU newspapers and bulletins, 1968-1974 (Folder 38)
    - no title (Box C232)
      - Eichmann -- Jewish Museum, 1985-1986 (Folder 7)
    - no title (Box C233)